[Music]
so we were going to talk today
about uh reinventio reinventing
yeah uh art right you wanted to talk
about art
yes and the importance of art and maybe
some false notions we have about what
that is and or some
some limited notions we have about what
that is and
and how do we make art relevant again
um for this time and which means going
again like all of our discussions to a
meta level
and saying what is art and what is the
function of art what is the function of
art for the human soul
uh and all that so this is you know this
is what i want to hear from you
you guys about which i think you might
get andrew i'd like to add one more
thing to that one more question one more
dimension
i'm actually also interested in what is
the role of art within
the logos and dialectic right i'm
interested in
this exploration of art for its own sake
sorry for the pun
uh but i'm also interested in this
exploration of
art for how i can better understand
the role and function of art within the
practice of dialectic and theologists
that's to me what's most uppermost on my
mind right now
okay um so that's interesting because i
think art is always a
dialectic of some kind um
i mean uh you know i've been a musician
and i've there's there's a dialectic
between the artist and the audience
there's what you're trying to express
and how people receive that and um
what do you what do you mean by that
what specifically
would art have uh what is
what does dialogues have to do with with
art
well thank you that's a very uh it's a
very platforming question you just gave
me
um so
i i remember i'm influenced by scary's
work on beauty and the way beauty trains
us for truth and justice
and we've already discussed that at
length um and i'm similarly influenced
by collingwood's notion
that what art does is get us to remember
um the non-categorical identity of
things
uh kind of the sexiness and and what
that brings me into is that i see what's
happening in art is a serious playing
with
and through our salience landscaping
and i think one of the things that art
can do for us
and one of the things art should do for
us is to take us into that liminal space
where we're trying to improve our
capacity for discernment
see so in i i'm also deeply influenced
by fisher's book
on you know uh the aesthetics of
the rainbow and rare experiences where
he talks about how art puts us on what
he calls the
horizon of intelligibility so i think
art therefore puts us into situations
that
at least superficially look like
bullshit
in that often in art so what what do i
mean
in art uh sorry in bullshit let's go
there first
in bullshit one of the defining features
of it is things are salient beyond our
understanding
things are sailing beyond our right our
our ability to grasp them
and we're just caught up in how salient
things are independent of our
understanding
but in art at least initially we seem to
be getting into something similar
where often especially in great works of
art right we're finding things salient
before we have an understanding often
art
is triggering
you incoh feelings and thoughts and
conceptions and so
when you say in kuwait you mean art gets
us in touch with
what we don't quite yet already know
exactly
exactly exactly so art is
often and this is what i take fisher to
mean by the horizon of intelligibility
right art is often ascending it's often
trying to point us
into a space beyond where we are
and now the thing about that is like i
said that at least is superficially very
similar to bullshit but there seems to
be a difference between them
um and and and fischer makes his
connection to socrates in his book
he talks about yeah but with art
right what's happening is that they're
you're experiencing a state of wonder
you're experiencing a state of opening
up
and trying to recover a deeper sense of
truth or realness
whereas in bullshit the opposite is
happening the opposite is happening is
one is pretending to know all that one
needs to know
and one has become indifferent to the
truth so wonder is an
opening so it's an extensive opening
where bullshit is an ostentatious
closing
so although they escape perhaps right
sometimes an escape but i think it's
more
what the bullshit artist wants you to do
is to not think anymore
right the bullshit artist is really
trying to get you caught up
in not thinking and not caring about the
truth that was frankford's central
notion
whereas the work of art where are it
well it might look like bullshit
initially because we're like we're
perplexed
but that wonder i think at least should
be
i don't know if it always is intended to
be but that wonder
should be in the service of drawing us
into
a deeper getting uh
re-awakening our concern for what
matters for what's real
right and so i think if that argument is
is
is plausible and this also maybe is the
difference
between actual art and let's say um
mindless entertainment which is yes
bullshit right
yeah yes exactly that's that's how i'm
trying that's exactly where i was going
to go with this andrew
so thank you for that foresight so if we
if we do have that kind of a distinction
one of the things art does for us in
contrast
to entertainment and this is an ancient
thesis that a lot of artists won't
initially like because of romanticism
but art has an
educational function in that what art is
supposed to do is
tutor us in it right into actively
learning how to discern between
bullshit and wonder how to actively
right allow our salience landscaping to
be restructured
in the service of the pursuit of
truth or a deeper connection as opposed
to as you said
an escape or an isolation or a
misdirection
right or as you said entertainment where
we just sort of try to cut ourselves
off for a while from reality i'm not
opposed to entertainment
but i'm opposed to entertainment as a
way of life um and i think art
when art is distinct from entertainment
art is helping to portend a way of life
for us
i'm going to jump on that a little bit
an independent but i think complementary
thought which is that the opening
the affordance of opening of worlding if
i can put it that way that art allows
is that art as a function i think one of
the things that it
does functionally is it helps to
transcribe
the logos of a given notion of again a
given encounter
into mythos it it it involves a
dispersal
of an experience into a landscape that
can then be regathered
and retrieved and cohered
as a world unto itself and so then made
sense of
and so then when it's recovered and
recollected it is recovered and
recollected in such a way that it
is i think disposed more elegantly
right so that one of the things that art
actually allows us to do
is take the logos of a given experience
and telescope it out in an accordion
fashion
so that it can actually become something
to be traversed
and indwelled and known from within and
cohered from within
so that in the regathering of it it can
be known more fully and then
known through right so i think of
something like narrative narrative is
certainly by no means the only form of
art but i think
for for a good reason it's often a
canonical form when people give such
examples
storytelling for instance so one of the
things that storytelling does is it
takes a given pattern
and makes that pattern participable it
makes it traversable explorable and
infinitely discoverable right you make a
world
out of a concept a world out of a notion
and
and your encounter with the notion
speciates encounters
that can then be re-gathered and cohered
in your understanding your episteme of
that particular pattern
and i think i think that the function of
art has something to do with the
speciating of different forms of
encounter
from our ultimate encounter with the
logos
are you saying that art has like a
parabolic function yes
yes exactly the way in the republic
uh you know socrates proposes blowing
the psyche up
magnifying it into the state so that we
can get a better understanding of it
politically and then we can
re-internalize that back and become
different because of that is that yes
exactly like as if you know let's say
let's say our our intent is to look to
know the logos of nature
one of the things that art does is it it
produces the flora
and fauna that allow us to explore it so
that we can better gather
and re-gather and re-gather still with
with appreciating precision perhaps
ontologically the logos of nature at
large
and and and there's some so there's
something exploratory about art that
actually allows us to to
i think this is a neoplatonic idea
although i think gadamer talks about it
a little bit too
that we disperse it so as to better
recover it
so as to recollapse it together this is
one question i have
uh and and that is you know in plato's
republic
plato is quite sensorious about about
art right yeah
art should be like this and not like
this and he's very particular
so that the danger is art becomes a kind
of moralism right
it becomes a kind of uh uh tale of
uh good or evil right where sometimes
you know in edgar allan poe when when
the guy is stabbing the the the cat with
a knife
this is like that's the thing that opens
you up it does
has doesn't have any kind of um
[Music]
educational or moralistic quality to it
it's just opens you up to
to a kind of naked perspective so
i hear you john and i agree that art has
this sort of educational
uh quality but but then i'm afraid
of it becoming a kind of moralism yeah i
wasn't i wasn't trying to add i
i i uh advocate for that i agree with
what you're saying andrew
i was trying to and i want to gather
together with what just said it
amplified you
i was trying to i was trying to open up
an aspect i was
of art that i would answer the question
you posed to me
which was what's its relationship to
dialectic and so i
i was proposing to that in a way
analogous to how philosophy
plays with concepts art plays with our
centaurium
our salience landscaping and our enacted
intelligibility just like
chris says he's i think he's proposing a
specific way in which art
uh does this silence landscaping because
it's a training in wonder
it's a training and wonder where wonder
is something that allows us to discern
between the opening up right to
something
more than what we have seen or known and
bullshitting which which
blocks us down and disconnects us from
concern with the truth
see the thing about poe is poe is there
is still the aesthetic there that i'm
talking about
because you know the moments in po those
those moments of horror
right horror is another way of getting
you outside of the categorical
like identity of things those moments of
horror we realized potential in
the in the world that we couldn't
realize before and
and post horror is directed towards
getting us to
to be more in touch with reality as it
is poe is trying to break
through the veneer of civilized
existence and remind us no no
remember underneath all of this veneer
there is
this and this is really there so i think
poe
actually is a good example of exactly
what i'm talking about
because i think horror well we've talked
about this i think horror and awe and
wonder
are all on a continuum and so i think
horror is a way in which we telescope
the way chris is saying our salience
landscaping so that we can move
into we can seriously play ourselves
into that liminal space
where we can wonder again about
ourselves and the world but if that
became too explicit
or or then then it would lose its power
somehow
it has to be very angular or something
it has to be
it shouldn't be philosophy art shouldn't
be philosophy
yeah right now that art shouldn't be
philosophy i keep saying that because
that's exactly what i'm saying i think
art is working with a different
part of our cognitive faculties that
you know that need to be addressed and
educated independent
of our capacity for reflective
conceptualization very much
but you see i've noticed that whenever
whatever degree i've been trained in an
art i've noticed that
what happens is i get a training in this
kind of discernment
that i'm talking about and again it's
not it's not a it's not a propositional
it's an actual
sensory motor discernment that allows me
to
distinguish between when people are
manipulating the salience
to bullshit me and when they're manipu
when they're
manipulating the salience in such a way
that i yeah i don't know i'm slightly
confused but that confusion is
ultimately towards a good end because
that's why air is so important because
it doesn't really allow you to bullshit
some of it like well you can't it's good
propositionally bullshit
you can't make something you can make a
kind of simulacrum of something
and it's but you know that it's a fake
right uh if if you have the eye of
discernment and can tell what is a
genuine work of art you know what is
bullshit
and what it is that's that's part of the
the work of of contemplating a worker
i think that's that's exactly it i'm
trying to situate
think about think about how we train
discernment we train the sermon by
by by putting ourselves into contrasting
situations and i'm saying
art gets us like art is training us to
discernment in contrast to entertainment
on one side and propaganda on another
because
propaganda looks like art but i think
it's basically
doing that kind of thing it's actually
trying to make you not think it's trying
to bullshit you
it's trying to get you self-enclosed
within an ideological framework
yeah right which is why art is really
i think one of its functions is to take
the closed ends of the world
and make them porous again yes right to
reopen
the world in such a way that the that
the the to to
perhaps to refrain to some of the
language we've been using in our
previous discussions to take this to
take the such of an encounter and use it
as a way of presencing the want for more
yes exactly right that's why there's an
inherent and implicit errors to art is
that it's somehow
it's somehow recollective of its own
finitude its own limitations and it and
it
constantly ostends beyond itself from
the species of a particular thing
to to the more of whatever the parent of
that species happens to be that elusive
parent that it's trying to retrieve
um and and then and then to draw the
affinity between those two things and to
cl and to to continue to
close of course it can't it's it's it's
not because it's inexhaustible it can't
ultimately be closed
but to try and mediate the relation
between
the suchness of specificity in that
regard and then the
and and then the moreness of what's
unbounded there's a there's a beautiful
well we're talking about poe we may as
well throw another author into the mix
there's a
short story or a novella i guess
by tolstoy called um family happiness
and and and right at the beginning of of
this novella there's a
there's a young a young woman she's a
teenage girl and she
um and it's and it's a summer
it's over over the course of the summer
time and and
you know they live out in the country
her and her family and they're visited
regularly by this family friend who's a
little bit older a little wiser
you know has has but but uh but
but but countenance is a lot of warmth
and is a very good friend of the family
and as as this man starts visiting them
more and more regularly this this young
woman
begins to find in each of her artistic
encounters
a kind of renewed vitality
a kind of participatory valence a kind
of
life-giving energy out of playing music
out of taking walks out of out of you
know
darning clothes out of all kinds of all
of these craft-oriented activities that
she's undertaking
habitually in the course of her daily
life take on this
pregnancy they take on this great sense
of independent vitality
and then she realizes at one point she
has this insight
where she actually realizes that all of
the these
these new loves that she is encountering
and all of these different forms of arts
and crafts
are all species of the same love that
she has for this man
that has been visiting and so these
these arts become a way of affining
the specific encounters that she has
with any one of these activities
with the way in which they are all being
gathered and the force in virtue of
which they are all being gathered
which isn't to say that this man is the
end of love but that he becomes a symbol
unto the form of love that all of these
separate encounters
are being gathered and cohered by and in
the undertaking of all of these
different activities
and they're cohering together she comes
to this
this this more this this fuller
understanding of what such a thing means
and so i think in some ways that's what
i mean by the like it's the dispersal
out
and then the retrieval of in order to
gather it into
into something by which to see so
so that's a process of cognitive
evolution and yeah
that's a process by which we're evolving
right we're evolving
our our you know our capacity for
sensory motor interaction with the world
because
you're sending out like you said you're
sending out all the variations your
speech
you even use the language of speciating
and then you put right and then you try
to gather back
what is it that they all gather to and
belong to
and then of course that's not going to
stop there presumably
you know you're going to keep having
that kind of cycle
and that's what i mean about i think how
art is there's this
yeah there's this it's kind of it's kind
of an educated
socially constructed evolution
of our sensorium in a in in a very
comprehensive manner
yeah i can relate to to what you're
saying um
kristoff in terms of my you know in my
20s i wrote a lot of songs
and i i think the songs that i wrote
that had some quality
to them probably were written without me
being able to like they took me over on
some level
they were not propositional in any way
they were like something i discovered
it's like wow what's this
um and i didn't know what i was doing at
all and that would
the more i didn't know what i was doing
the more i was in in
an area that was alive which sounds like
a kind of romanticism so
i was throwing all these things out
there and they would
form something that was and when i
became much more
conscious of what i was doing was harder
to do it was much harder to
to actually construct something like
it's hard to construct a work of art i
think
it seems to be reliant somehow on on
inspiration on something
beyond does that make any sense um
yeah i think it relies on the i mean
speaking as a cognitive scientist i
think what we have this term that's not
very helpful creativity
and i think creativity is a way of
pointing to
uh you know cognitive processes of
insight
uh meta metaframing processes where
we're switching between italic mode and
the peritonic mode
there's all these processes at many
levels of cognitive
analysis at which we engage in a
restructuring
of what we find salient and relevant not
by doing something you can't do it you
can't do an insight
right but what we do is we do things
that trigger the process to
self-organize
and then we bear witness to that
epiphany
to use roots and uh very pregnant phrase
that's what
that's what i think actually happens the
most of the work actually is is not
actually the artistic expression it's
just training it's just training
and it's just opening yourself up for
some kind of
muse or spirit to arrive at your
doorstep and
on some level but that's exactly yeah
you have to
you have to write a lot of bullshit out
of your system before i mean i know this
for writing poetry for
for decades you have to write a lot out
and that's what i mean about
we we we tend to focus too much on the
product of art
and what i'm trying to do right now in
this in what we're saying
and this is how i think it's connected
to the dialectic is focus
get us to focus on the process of art
what what
what has to happen right in people's
development
in what virtues and sensibilities do
they need to cultivate
such that the things that we call art
are produced by them
rather than fixating on the product and
trying to determine what art is from
that
that's what i'm suggesting that's i
think that's absolutely right i think it
also serves to explain why you know
a lot of artists will tell you at least
the prodigious ones will tell you that
they dis-identify
from the products from whatever whatever
is whatever arena
is spontaneously created in the
encounter with an experience or the
encounter with a mode of inquiry it's
the
the arena that's produced for the
purposes of practicing agency
whatever is left behind in that arena
once the agency
is evolved and practiced and practices
its way out of that arena whatever is
left over in the arena is in a way
incidental it's incidental at least
to the to the to the to the
development of character that it has
affected
and also also it can trap the artist
like
he can he can create a product and that
that can define him
yeah exactly and then and then he slips
into the hopping mode
he doesn't get stuck in the having mode
and he doesn't exactly
he doesn't keep learning because he
becomes uh he becomes
his the image of himself as an artist
and his product becomes crystallized
so he can't transform in the way it is
necessary
um to continue to create a living art
you know yes yes which often i what i
find is and that was
what i thought when john was speaking
was the problem is is almost
youth in a sense in terms of how we see
art you know in popular culture is that
people get famous or and they create art
very young and then
they don't have a full life as an artist
because they become defined
in in some kind of a way and that um
some kind of
maturing process has to has to occur
for an artist to be a generative
personality instead of a destructive
one i think that's very well said very
well
so my concern is
that there should be some there's some
transfer relationship
between this training and discernment so
we can
reliably discriminate between bullshit
and wonder
that that that should that that should
find a place within
dialectic as a practice and via logos as
a process
that's what i mean about their that's
how i think art
right and the fact that dialogos is
committed to emergence
it's committed to taking us to like the
horizon of intelligibility
that it's committed to getting us to see
things in their non-categorical identity
again we're trying to do it right now
we're trying to reinvent the
art we're trying to step outside of the
categories i see all of that
as finding a proper home within
dialectic so i do think that there's
deep connections between the practice of
art and the practice of dialectic
yeah i also know people have kind of a
limited idea of what art is
it's it's it's limited to the
performance or the plastic arts or
music or or whatever but fundamentally
your whole life should be an art on some
level i mean
maybe that's a grandiose statement but
but um
[Music]
well i think that's making sense here i
know we have to distinguish
it's an artistic process and and what is
you know what is painting and music and
that kind of thing but
i i i want i want there to be a larger
definition of of the project of heart
some narrow sort of uh activity of
you know playing guitar and writing a
song or painting a painting or
but but that that was nietzsche's hope
right
but the problem is the way that the term
he used the term he
originated has degenerated and it no
longer has that reference
nietzsche came up with the idea of a
lifestyle and the whole point about a
lifestyle was exactly what you were
articulating thereafter
it was trying to bring the like the the
the education and and evolution
in in the practice of art into one's
life as a whole
because he was trying to come up with a
non-religious or maybe post-religious
way
for the cultivation of virtue because he
saw the need for it and he came up with
the idea of lifestyle but the problem
with the idea of
lifestyle right and if you read when he
talks about it he's got these amazing
passages of
you're trying like you're all of the
impulses within you are
and you're trying to shape them into
something right and it's
and that's not what it means anymore
lifestyle has been generated into
you know a particular fashion uh
or branding of oneself uh that has
nothing to do with what nietzsche was
talking about
but i think the idea of right having
um an aesthetic even this isn't gonna be
deep enough but something like a
profound aesthetic style to one's
existence
as an ideal for one's life i think
that's
exactly what nietzsche was trying to
talk about
yeah maybe the issue with nietzsche is
that his idea was too
much based on the individual artist
yes rather than perhaps the collective
experience of creating art in
in in a community or with other people
or which which i don't know you can be a
solo artist or you can be in a band
uh you know uh
i think yeah i think his antipathy
towards
socrates and plato are really blocked
him from seeing
um the sort of dialogic and distributed
aspects
of art i think that's true and i think
also i find
like he lost he lost the idea about the
dynamic balance between the apollonian
and the dionysian within the work of art
like if you look right
the spirit you know the birth of tragedy
from the spirit of music it's clear that
the two are supposed to be
um you know held in equal balance
because that he becomes increasingly
antagonistic towards the apollonian
right as he goes on and i think that's
also
um very detrimental to his his overall
argument
[Music]
right so we need to keep in mind then
the choral elements
as we talked about i think in our last
conversation the three of us right we
talked about the core
the choral elements of dialectic and
dialogue says
foundational to its place yeah uh
related yeah
coral as in relating to the chorus um
that are that are fundamental to its
situation within meta dialogue
right that the the the choral presence
is what we mean by
the more of the meta dialogue that helps
to
to gather the relevance of whatever is
situated within a particular practice
yeah because i'm sorry to interrupt but
but it's not an individual expression
is it it goes decidedly not you know we
kind of consider art to be an individual
expression of some kind
even if you're a solo artist i i don't
think it's an individual expression
no it's i think that's kind of a lot
that's kind of one of the lies of how we
consider art to be it's about expressing
yourself
but i think yes you're right if you have
the coral the coral is always working
with you
and and you're you're synthesizing all
of these voices
in into some unique expression that
that's beyond you
well i think it's more i i i i'm
actually arguing
against the romantic proposal that art
is fundamentally self-expression i i'm
actually
arguing that art is fundamentally a form
of self-cultivation
and self-transformation um and that
you're not trying to express
you're trying to make a new way of being
possible for yourself and for others
a work of art like chris said he said
this a few minutes ago
it should open it should give you a
serious play and practice
of opening up another world that's what
a great work of art does for you
like ultimately like ultimately
if if you are not already pre-committed
to an unjustified individualism why is
self-expression
such a valorized thing who cares
i mean really i'm saying i'm not trying
to be i'm not trying to be like
cruel i mean but who cares like like
what is that for
well i mean i would search for something
universal in a song not something about
me
if i was trying to write a song yeah it
would have to be it would be something
that would
would would ground me in a larger
community and and make me confront
myself
now that rather than rather than give me
a strong definition of who i am
yeah you don't want to be planting a
flag on yourself that's not what art
should be
right i mean well our art art works with
the material of the self it's
self-cultivation
but i mean it's ultimately right i mean
the meaning all the meaning in life
literature shows that what
really gives us meaning in life is to be
is to matter
to be connected to something beyond
ourself that has a value independent of
our egocentric concerns
self-expression by definition fails that
project so it fails to contribute to
meaning in life
that's why i'm getting so passionately
critical of it whereas if i'm engaging
in self-cultivation
that transforms me such that i become a
vehicle for a world opening up to other
people
that is mattering that is making a
difference beyond myself
and that is meaningful i was
i was listening to your video with
jonathan pagio um
today and oh yes he's a very fine artist
yes but he and he's also also in a way
he's a traditionalist
right because he wants to create icons
and i guess
at the time when icons were being
created you were looking through the eye
of god
right probably like that that and then
suddenly humanism came along in what
13th 14th century
and you're supposed to look through the
eye of yourself
okay and then i don't know maybe you
could you know more about the history of
ideas than me john but then i guess we
have einstein and relativity
and then we have when you have
post-modernism and then
the self starts to dissolve and then
there is no such thing as a self anymore
and
um so i was thinking about the beauty of
what jonathan
does and and i was also thinking of
about my desire for post-traditional art
as well
and what would that look like because
i'm not just satisfied with with
iconography and i do think there's
something
modern about what he's doing at the same
time i i don't want to
accuse him of being uh being um you know
but you know but but at the same time
you know i think iconography is is a
beautiful form of expression but
but but there is something to modern art
is there not that that
is perhaps close i don't know to zuchin
or
something like that's not narrative or
yeah i'm throwing out a lot of ideas
here excuse me
am i am i can you pick up on any of that
yeah i did i picked up uh i picked up on
a few things and then i'll turn things
over to chris
i think the one of the great importances
important things about modern art
whatever that is supposed to point to
is precisely the fact that it reminds
us of the possibility of non-narrative
wonder
of non-narrative uh self-cultivation it
liberates us
i i don't think it should be seen as
excluding narrative because as chris
rightly says
narrative is a important feature of
many genres of art but modern art uh
tried to liberate us from that to some
degree because
i think it would and i i you see this in
uh
uh oh what's the name of the guy who oh
he was synesthetic start with a k
he wrote the spiritual name yes
yeah yes right and he talked you can see
clearly and he's one of the fathers of
modern art right
he he's he he sees the abstract
as a way of freeing us from narrative as
a way of freeing us from egocentrism
as a way of get bringing back the sacred
in art
so i i think that that is an important
value
in it um now i don't think that that's a
problem for jonathan because as you said
jonathan sees these as icons he sees
them as
you know windows but you have to
remember remember eckhart you did
the i by which you see god is the same
eye by which he sees you
it's not right right it's it's it's it's
a transjective bi-directional thing
jonathan sees that but for people caught
in
humanism they don't have that there
isn't that translucency
right and so i think what modern art was
trying to do
when it when it went post-humanist and
went abstract
right at least initially kadinsky you
can see this
is it's trying to open us back up to the
transit going
by liberating us from the narrative
because
ego and narrative are very bound
together very inter-defining
so i think your allusion to it being
something like a buddhist having a
buddhist
component to it i think that's well
placed i think that's well said
yeah there seems to be a tension between
the narrative and the post narrative
story and maybe they're both necessary
um well i like the discussion between
sort of
uh non-duality and and person that
person
should there be a person personal god
versus sort of the impersonal versus the
person
those two have to be i think those two
we have to transcend the non-duality and
also transcend the personal but they
both have to
come together yeah i think i think that
is properly the project of non-theism
uh but yeah i i think that's right i i
think that
i mean there's there's areas of art that
maybe we don't there's areas of art that
maintain a closer connection
to the sacred precisely because they
have this structure
you just said you know there's where you
have a narrative structure that
undermines
its narrative and undermines any it
destabilizes you trying to take up
any self-satisfied ego role within them
that's exactly what the parables of
jesus are
the parables of jesus are these
narratives like when you read
parable of the product of the sun you
think there's this story but when you
try to put yourself in
any of the roles you fund you fall under
god's judgment
right they don't work and and you know
and sally mcfag does all this great work
on and the soupies have similar things
where the parables are narratives that
then
deconstruct themselves as narratives
because they're designed to
explode you beyond an egocentric uh
way of being and i think
so i think that's what i meant what i
was trying to say earlier about
you know there's almost and you can see
how this could go together with what
chris is saying you can see how a
parable right
gets you to telescope out the
intelligibility in the narrative
but then it collapses the narrative and
you get the re-gathering
and you have to transcend to something
in that regathering so it's not just a
gathering back
it's a gathering that then pushes you
beyond this the
the space that was originally drawn by
the narrative and i think in that sense
we should we should we should talk more
often in our culture
about appropriate connections between
art and parable
that and and i think that's something
that
uh that needs to be explored more and
more right now
because we've gotten too much into
again like you said art as a product
that is some
kind for art's sake yeah which i don't i
i ultimately don't agree
agree with uh exactly we shouldn't be
we shouldn't be creating wonderful
trophies uh of self-expression
we should be we should be creating
parables that constantly propel us
beyond ourselves
yeah well that it seems to be that for
all of the reasons that art
those instances where we those instances
where we believe of art of any given
instance of it that it is genuine art
right because there's a little bit of a
there's kind of a normative distinction
i think uh uh a kind of ineffable
normative distinction that people make
when they say some this is real art they
don't even
we don't typically we don't even know
what we mean by that when we say it but
you hear people saying it all the time
ah you see
that story or that novel or that show or
that whatnot
that's real art as opposed to this other
pulpy stuff
and i think like what what that is what
that means
um well uh yeah i think that part of
what that means
which i think is is is which
refers back to everything that the two
of you have just said in the last three
minutes
is that when when
when the purported subject of art
whatever it
happens to be at the top and the time
seems to become conscious that it
lives in reference to some necessity
snares guided by that that it is not of
itself or for itself but that
it exists only in so far it is it exists
as a gesture
a beyond word gesture away from itself
i think under those circumstances we say
of something that it is true or genuine
art
and so i that when you were talking
about the idea of
self-expression i thought that was kind
of interesting and you spoke of it both
of you spoke
the idea of self-expression pejoratively
but i think and and
fairly so but if we were to
to capitalize the s at the end of that
self i think we would find
that that expression took on something
of a different meaning
because it would recollect divine double
then right
exactly it would be an expression of the
divine double if what art is is
self-expression and perhaps
also simultaneously self-impression that
it is
mimetic it is my medic of the inarable
it's
mimetic of something that has not been
fully retrieved right
and it's we are it and that and that
brings
that brings into the question of art
this idea of ontological conformity
that if what it is doing is trying to
get itself into conformity of that which
is not
imminently retrievable then it becomes a
way of
rendering an impression of a self yet
undiscovered
that capital self that divine double
cell for the sacred second self
right and so every time you produce
something
there is a kind of there is a kind of
attempted imitation at
the self that is out of reach to bring
it into presence
and it's not that you would have to
express that self perfectly
it would it would be that you would have
to gesture towards it i would say i
would say that's right
and that is you're not going to express
it the word a work of art is a gesture
it's not a complete um uh
telling of what that is that's right
which is why it has to be translucent
right it has to be porous it has to its
boundaries have to be permeable because
it's not
it's an it's approximation it's ever
ever approximation it's ever
approximation right
that's why a true i'm sorry i keep
coming back to narrative not not because
it's essentially
the case but just because it's the most
easily retrievable example for me
but one of the things that one of the
things that we find in a truly truly
truly good story
is that its specificity seems to provide
the current
for a universality and those things seem
to be and there seems to be an entity
there they seems to be in contradiction
but of course they're not right because
the more such the such of the story is
the more it seems to presence the
possibility of being more
the more it's the more it's mimetic
finessing
seems to gather its arms around
something of of appreciating realism
that's why magical realism as a form of
narrative is often so powerful
because magical realism as a as a
sub-genre of narrative
seems to actually make a narrative
conscious of this very dynamic
but that's that's when it gets that's
when it gets parabolic chris
exactly yeah that's i'm saying this is
all very this is all convergent with
that observation
yeah parabolic is is is that different
than let's say uh symbolic
um yeah i think what's the difference
because because
you would say that we need parabolic art
and i would say i find
symbolism and art very powerful and i
think jonathan pagio was sort of
showing us that um and that we've sort
of lost our
um symbolic literal uh literacy like
we're
symbolically illiterate a bit and so
people used to express themselves in
these powerful symbols
and now now people are are often
creating something that is a very
poor kind of realism right it's like a
documentary style it's just
it's just uh it's like werner herzog
says it's like reading the phone book
it's like
you try to create realism but it doesn't
have that magic to it because
because realism in a sense is is is the
bullshit
that it's real realism um yeah
i think that's right um i don't think
these i don't think those two claims are
in competition with each other
i think they're they they should be
unfolded together i think i agree with
you and i agree with jonathan
that really you know and i know chris
does too you know
recovering our symbolic sensibilities in
a proper way
a wise way a way that affords
discernment is exactly one of the things
that art should be doing especially
right now uh
but but i think if we oh well let's take
what jonathan makes
the icon right the point about the point
about the icon is it's ultimately
parabolic
right if you get locked into the icon
right
then you you turn it into an idol that's
what john mcmarian talks about right
in the god beyond being right you right
it always has to have this parabolic
structure to it because
it has to meet you where you are but
then it has to explode
so that you are propelled beyond
infinite expression and
as as as christoph says porous right
that's what immediate
and translucent rather than a fixed
closed system
exactly the thing it has to do is it has
to like
chris is right though right it's it's
not an amorphous infinite
right it's it's not the indeterminate
it's the infinite that has been poured
into the finite so that it glows
with something beyond the finite but is
never anything other than
finite for you right that that's the
that's the that's what i'm trying to get
out
and and and the notion that chris was
mentioning about
uh the self-expression with the castle
capital s as he was saying that i was
thinking of one of his favorite
authors somebody who actually transcends
the boundary between
uh philosophy and art which maybe
undermines what i said a few minutes ago
but i'm thinking of kirkegaard and
thinking about how kirkegaard writes
these parabolic narratives
that are designed right to do exactly
what we're talking they're designed to
sort of suck you into a particular role
and then explode that role so that you
come to realize
that you have within you something that
is the potential for any and every role
and that that's something your soul has
a relationship to something much more
ultimate
than any one of these roles or ways of
life and again i think that's
one of the pre if that's what you mean
by self-expression chris
that's what i can i can agree with that
yeah yeah no that's beautifully said
that's precisely it precisely it yeah
i just don't like i just don't like the
phrase because of its sort of standard
meaning
right yeah of course of course and and i
wouldn't be inclined to use it either
but if we were to if we were to
try and recall something of an original
meaning
within the commonplace expression it
would require that minor
augmentation i think that was my only
point in saying that um
just as a way of of playing with it i
mean part of our practice of reinventio
here is to take what is common
and play with its communists as a way of
recollecting its original meaning
um and and this is i think that's all
just part of the same
um practice well i don't think it's
happenstance that you mentioned those
two because i think there's deep
connection
between how we're talking about art and
the practice of inventio
where we're trying to get between we're
trying to get between inventing
and discovering that's what we're
talking about here may i raise a
question for
all of us because i think it was also
implicit in what andrew was asking
and we've lost the thread and i want to
make sure we go back to it which is
does art have to be beautiful
right so i've argued that we should be
concentrating more on the process
rather than the product but does the
process
always have to be in service of being
drawn by
induced by beauty or are there other
things
that properly afford and draw art
out into the world
i i would stage on that beauty the
practice of art is not suffused
constantly with beauty but it is
constantly
guided by its search right
that like i i'm just thinking on a on a
very
i thinking on a very hands-on
just trying to the process of trying to
produce something whatever it may be
right whether trying to produce a paper
or trying to produce a song
which i have no experience with andrew
but you'll be able to just be
stupid you know it's it's mostly um
i think you're i think you're i it it
yeah yeah
yeah i believe it i believe it's the
most irritating thing in the world right
but it's kind of laborious right it's
glorious and irritating
because and it's melodies get in your
head and you hate them
and you somehow have to go to the end on
some level and get the thing out
it's like as i said the midwife it's
like you have the birth
yeah right right the eras right because
the era the eras right the
the in the the the instinct of eros is
guided by beauty but that doesn't mean
that every
that that the um that that eros is
is always disposed to be beautiful
though it seeks beauty
and i think perhaps that's the
difference is that the the air the
erosive art is is guided
attentionally in the pursuit of beauty
but
it's it's incidence is not always
beautiful
just as i would say that my answer to
john's question is that
um yes art always has to be beautiful
but our definition of what beauty is is
probably problematic
usually because we think of beauty in in
in a very narrow
sentence yeah yeah and that beauty
itself
can can be found in the most
banal it can be found in something
grandiose it can be found in the baroque
it can be found in
it can be found anywhere and in any
circumstance and
and so it doesn't have to it doesn't
have to conform to let's say a platonic
ideal of what beauty is
or symmetry or any of that but
but i i'm not sure if i i've answered
the question myself but i think the
answer is yes that art has to be related
to beauty
but we also have to broaden the notion
of what what beauty is
to not be something um cliche and and
you know very well let's
let's play with this because i want to
by the way i just want to make no
tell you in the middle of art you were
invoking midwifery
which of course is also the project of
socratic dialectic
yeah but socrates dialogue with yourself
you know yeah don't you call that the
vertical dialectic or something like
that you're dialoguing with with higher
powers or
um but but let's play with this what you
guys have both said
so what came to my mind when i asked
this question
was it was a painting that i've often
found very powerful and i consider it a
bonafide
great work of art many other people do
is picasso's guernica
right guernica um which
is it's hard it's hard for me to when
i'm standing in the presence of that
uh painting to say i'm experiencing
anything like beauty
i'm experiencing shock horror
i i'm experiencing um even the
perversion of the sacred you know how he
has that big
yes the light at the top that's taking
the the electric light that's taking the
place of god
right in the painting uh and and and yet
all of this is because
and this is where collingwood's idea
comes in and that's why i'm asking this
question
because collingwood says that because he
actually uses this example
collingwood said the point of that is to
try and get us and i'm going to use the
language we've been using
is picasso doesn't want us to think of
the
battle of the bombing of guernica
categorically
he doesn't want us to swat it in all the
other bombings all the other tragedies
he wants us to directly experience the
ineffable
horrible suchness of that moment the
non-categorical
ah of guernica that can't be captured
categorically because only that horror
is appropriate
to the tragedy that was unfolding that's
the
right relationship to the event yeah so
you see you see what i'm i'm not saying
that i've refuted you guys or anything
like that
i'm trying to say that isn't it any
beauty is the relationship
uh like between you and the dating it's
not the painting itself
it's it's the relationship it affords
that's what came to mind
well okay so that's what i that's what i
was wondering because it is
in the picking example what you said
andrew i've been trying to reorient this
off the product of our to the process
can we reorient from a product notion of
beauty
to a process notion of beauty yeah
i think that's right because that's what
we have to do in fact
um so some of what some of what you seem
to be just describing john is that
one thing one experience you have when
you look at the picasso painting
is that yes so it it it
it accommodates an uncategorical
experience
of of such a
phenomenon but what it also does i think
in in in the way that you you've given
i can't remember where this example
comes from originally it might be yours
john but when you talk about the
suchness of the trees and the moreness
of the trees that you encounter a
beautiful tree
such that it is unique and incomparable
and you also encounter in this beauty of
the same tree
the the the just the the infinite
possibility of treeness and all of its
beauty
and then i think so then one way then of
thinking about art and the way that
you've just described it with this
example
is and i think you just said this andrew
is an appreciation of the relation
between those two uncategorical
categories
of the the infinite more of the beauty
of something
and the and the such of its beauty
and being able to relate those two and
two
and two and to um
to intimate and make more intimate their
dialogue
in the experience of a given work oh so
if you'll allow me to be slightly poetic
then what you're saying is
that picasso's guernica uh actually
presences
the soul of the battle yeah
and yeah was it's the courage of the
artist
to to express that in its most naked
form
which also makes it beautiful yes i
think i i think there is a connection to
i mean he's definitely trying to train
discernment
in fact it's hard to justify um the
the that that painting without it having
that
if it just sort of horrified me
towards no end right but what he what
he's i mean
i mean his intent was ultimately even
political there right
he was trying to wake people up he was
trying to get them to discern
uh what was actually going on in this
battle
uh in a profound way yeah so it's not
highly shock
value which is that's one of the
problems with
with contemporary art right yes exactly
that's right and the shock
and the shock does not have the
conjugate doesn't have content to it
it doesn't because it doesn't have the
same kind of invocation because the
shock
actually dissociates from its realism
rather than impressing it
the shock actually doesn't conjure the
soul of an experience
what shock does is actually i find what
shock does is actually
dissociate from the soul of an
experience
so this idea of this idea of
art being a kind of being a way of
presencing the logos um
i think being a way of presencing and
this this then goes back
to to the idea you brought up andrew of
of of um of the
the renewing this renewing
so what it does i think in some ways is
it it it makes
of a particular rendering a symbol that
presences
the soul of the logos
[Music]
so this then circles back to the
argument i made
that virtue is the beauty of wisdom
so there is a process so a relational
transactive
process notion of beauty that is
appropriate then
and then would ally with our attempts to
redirect
the discussion of art off the product
and onto the process again
yeah off the it and and back to the vow
exactly that's well right right
beautiful beautiful so that the product
the product serves to invocate the
process
yeah so this and to and to reproduce it
to midwife it again yeah product has to
not
not be like a campbell soup can it has
to
as it has to well it has to go beyond
the campbell soup can
right and keep reproducing itself it has
to be generative that's the word i was
thinking of when i was asked to be
focused
you know you watch some films and then
you just feel you know when i watch
these like expensive superhero movies
that everybody avengers and
people think are so great i just feel
exhausted afterwards like i feel like
i've been depleted of energy
but then there's other films you watch
like i imagine werner herzog's film
somehow they they have this texture and
depth to them and you
watch them and you feel like you've you
you've been nourished
in some kind of a way right you haven't
been like you know
you know that's what plato says right
you know
art can be a kind of rape you know it
can be like not art but
cheap entertainment it can be kind of it
rapes it rapes your soul
but the real kind of art is just like a
an opening of of as you say arrows
it is and it's infinitely realizable for
that very reason right the difference
between watching
the good film and the bad film right or
the strong film the artful film and the
unartful film is that the artful film
the artful film is you can interrogate
it
endlessly because when it when it when
it ext when it articulates itself out
the um it there's
there's something that is shining forth
through the medium
of the the work that is not of
of of the work itself and you don't you
don't that that's not
um that's not true of of every year
again i think that depends on the
integrity of the artists it's a little
bit what you know john is saying about
um you know all of these uh
like um qualities like wisdom and virtue
if the artist
is being motivated by that by by
those those qualities you know that
integrity
then that then that shines through if
he's being motivated by
by some kind of um something else
who knows what that other thing is
probably
trying to please uh the mob or something
uh
then then then it comes off as being uh
you know empty so there's two things
that came out of what you guys were just
talking i kept interrupting and i
shouldn't though
because you guys kept unfolding more um
what when andrew to gather back to
previous discussions we had we talked
about this how plato talks about
you know the the beauty is
like when we're talking about hans work
that the responsive beauty should not
ultimately be consumptive it should be
generative
the response to beauty is the desire to
generate more beauty and then you guys
linked that i think very astutely to the
to the notion uh you know of the
inexhaustible
an inexhaustible fountain of
intelligibility and then what you did
to my mind and tell me if you don't like
this but you wear beauty and art and
sacred
as all intertwined and interwoven
together
that sacredness because that's what it
is when we find something
an inexhaustible fountain of
intelligibility and that we find
within it a beauty that makes us want to
generate beauty
isn't that a really good definition of
the sacred
yeah absolutely it it also starts to
explain why art
art whatever alleges to be art if it
does not
if it does not invoke the sacred it
appears not to be art
you know the same activity perhaps that
means that
this is what does that mean like because
art can contain all kinds of
unsacred things and that again
but again your point is it the process
or the product we're talking about here
if the point is to put those unticked
things in to
wake us up from how we have perhaps turn
them into idols
or perhaps why we've lost touch with
their original meaning or
if it's to wake us up to the sacred
again that i think it's art if it's just
to be irreverent
then i don't think that would count as
good art to my mind
no i mean what we're doing here is we're
critiquing i mean we have launched
a deep critique of you know the romantic
slogan arts for ark's sake
we're saying art to be art should never
be for art's sake
yes and we're also making an implicit
platonic argument that
only good art qualifies the definition
yes yes if if it is not of the good
if the art is not of the good then it is
not art by definition which is a very
platonic argument
somehow i think that i think that it
can't be narrowed
to to platonic ideals because i because
that would
that would that would that would be
didactic or
is that the right word um well maybe
i'm gonna ask you andrew to do what you
did earlier when i made a proposal
you said maybe we need to reinvent your
sense of beauty
to be appropriate to where the argument
is leading us like we have to go all the
way up and all the way down is what i
want to say we want to
you have to see the art and the garbage
we have to see the art in um
you know distorted electric guitars and
uh
you know okay yeah yeah we also have to
see art
and uh and and these you know uh
i don't want uh a moralistic christian
version of art i'm sorry jonathan
i'm sorry i don't want that i want the
ramones and the sex pistols too
uh even though they they are irreverent
but there's some authenticity
coming through there but absolutely
there is i don't think anything that
we've said in
my mind in my mind this is good to
resolve then in my mind nothing
nothing we've just said excludes
excludes the
grungiest forms of art imaginable to me
to me this definition includes all of
that because
because because we're we're we're
we're with a great breath we're trying
to expand
the definition of what we mean by beauty
in the first instance i don't think it
is to the exclusion of anything that
seems like it has dirt under its
fingernails i i don't see it as
excluding that
yeah and so i was proposing andrew that
we uh we do an inventio on
or i think we are already doing it an
inventory on
the sort of platonic notions of art
that's what i think is actually
happening here um i don't think it's
about
i think there has been a mistake and
plato bear some responsibility for this
and so do
uh some of the neoplatelets so i think
that's it's well said but i think there
has been a mistake of
reducing all of this to what nietzsche
would call the apollonian
and that should never be the case i mean
the frame making of the apollonia
always has to be inextricably wed to the
frame breaking of the dionysian or you
never get the insight
again that's right is cold right with
without
the apollonian generative chaos of the
of the of the of the um
i think that's unfair to the apollonian
because of of the way the dichotomy has
unfolded
i think the apollonian is supposed to be
warm but it's supposed to be warm it's
you know with light and with stable form
and the dionysian
is supposed to be the warmth of heat and
rupture they're both warm but they're
warm in different ways
they're generative in different ways
right i mean
i mean birth requires a really painful
breaking and separating
but but it also has to come into a
stable being
right a child or or or or or
it turns into a disaster um so
i i agree so with that that aspect of
the nation critique
of what i think fairly has been called
the platonic
i think that's right but i think what
chris was alluding to
was the notion that that is
i still think is recoverable from plato
of art as something
ultimately aspirational something that
is ultimately cultivating wisdom
as a defining feature of the art and i
do think that there
is wisdom to be found in
some of the things i mean i think
you know hendrix guitar riffs we were
definitely doing simultaneously frame
breaking and frame making
and he was talking about a way of being
a way of seeing the world
right he was that was what was going on
there i was thinking of cezanne who he
you know he mastered all the classical
forms
and then you know he he couldn't find
anything that
mattered to him and all that and so he
took a big bonfire and he just he burned
everything he'd ever done for
40 years and then he came up with this
sort of
a art where he would you know do the
mountain
you know of san victoria over and over
again millions of times from different
angles and you can see it and
you know that he threw out perspective
and invented color invented a whole new
form
it looks very much like a postcard to us
now but at that time it was something
radical yeah
through the destruction of the old right
and he had
the more you kind of destroy of that you
have there's this there's this
that's perhaps the dionysian is the
destructive exactly
exactly and i think if plato had been
more connected to his proposal
which i think he is really really
proposed
of the generativity as the primary
response
uh to the beauty he would have seen that
all generativity has within it
both the frame breaking dionysian and
the frame making
apollonian and this generosity let's say
of the theater right because
because that's what he was criticizing
right is the theater and all its
garishness and all that's
and he he yeah he he didn't like the way
i mean
poetry means something much more than it
means for us he didn't like because
poetry also meant
writing plays and right so he didn't
like the way
in which uh that was the
now it's clear that he likes sort of the
you know
some of the classics like sophocles
because
and he he clearly likes homer because he
cites when we're repeating but he wants
to rewrite them he wants to he wants
because but this circles us back around
because this is
see this this is plato's worry and this
is why i
propose it as the initial connect
question plato's
worried about people not being able to
tell the difference
between wonder and bullshit right that's
exactly what
what you're putting your finger on again
he was worried about the way in which
these things
can bullshit people yeah so he was
criticizing netflix uh
more or less like he was in a sense he
was criticizing this popular
sort of um well and he might have
ultimately been
wrong i think about some aspects of art
i don't wanna i don't wanna deify it but
what i'm saying is
plato i think was at least cottoning on
to the fact
that this stock can
very rapidly the evol devolve
into entertaining bullshit in which
people are self-satisfied
with not needing to learn
not needing to be educated i mean and
that's what bullshit again that's what
that's its defining feature
the point about a commercial about a
typical incident one of
frankfurt's a bullshit is to make you
stop questioning about the product
so that you'll buy it right if right
it's or the point of the commercial is
to make you to stop reflecting about the
candidate
and vote for them but the point of a
work of art is to make you
reflect more about this thing or make
you reflect more
about this person political then
it can art be political it's a question
well it depends i think it could be
political in the aristotelian sense of
politics whereas we are recognizing i
mean what i think
when i say not political i don't mean
politics in the aristotelian sets i mean
the aristotle's sense is that this idea
that most of our cognition is done and
should be done in distributed cognition
and that is where we are at as fast
unfortunately aristotle
by by an accident in history only wrote
monologues so that sort of got lost
but the political i mean insofar as an
artist
is trying to get us and i mean this word
now deeply
to wonder about distributed cognition
and its sacred capacity for us i think
it can properly be political art
to the degree to which it is not calling
us
to explore and try and refine ourselves
into a more conforming right
relationship with reality
to the region which is trying to get us
to be closed and finished
and think we have both you know break
the godellion
picture that we claim to have both
completeness and consistency
and we're all done so in that degree
when
when it tries to be ideological in that
it becomes propaganda
then it becomes propaganda that's
exactly what i would argue
yeah yeah yeah yeah
which is why which is why i think any
any
any ostensive work of art that has
prefigured
its objective to close the ends of the
world
into a knot that establishes firm
ideological boundaries
to me can never constitute good art
because it can never it can never
reflect
that right relation to the real
right and so to go back to one of our
examples i think guernica is an example
of political art
that is not ideological right he's just
trying to get us to
realize the evil the
truth of the ineffable evil
that human beings are capable of
inflicting on each other
and sometimes it doesn't even need to be
that extreme sometimes it's simply to
call into question the unquestioned
certitude of certain the prevailing
climb of false beliefs right i mean
that's
you know like one of the things one of
the one of the art forms i enjoy
most and and it's often a very low brow
art form if we're talking about that in
those terms
is comedy like stand-up comedy for me
like those that do it well
are among the greatest artists i think
of our time
precisely because they have a knack they
have a penchant for inducing the
apparatic experience
in relation to that which goes
unquestioned
and and that's why they're particular
forms of trends and the more transgress
like when they are artfully
transgressive in that way
they are profoundly profoundly powerful
for that very reason but but but i mean
part of that is
at least because i mean i would argue
that
humor i mean the thing of the advantage
that humor has then
um is that sorry the advantage that
comedy has in so far as it invokes humor
is that humor is engaging the machinery
of insight
and so it's already getting insight into
into play
they're like i mean if your jokes are
falling flat then there isn't any
insight in what you're doing
so the the the thing that i would then
ask you then is
chris i'm granting you that i think
comedy has a special role
because of the way it it invokes insight
it doesn't just
uh request it it actually we have to be
we have to we have to do insight in
order to follow the comedy so i think
that's a point in its favor
but but the but the opposite of course
is
um right many comedies are merely
entertaining right
yeah it's not that's right yeah yeah
yeah it's not it's not
it's not something being incidentally
humorous that makes it artful
it's the it's it's it's the provocation
of humor
in service of insight i think that is
the
art of the practice but i was going to
say i guess some people like lenny bruce
in the beginning they they did have
really something
powerful to say about you know about
about race and and
things like that and but the way
their way of putting it it was quite i
would say
beyond entertainment i mean you're
laughing at the worst parts of yourself
like
you're laughing at you're laughing at me
you know you're laughing at seeing
yourself
inside out you're laughing at seeing
your your um you know
the comedy is the best comedians are are
most self-mocking of themselves in the
sense right right
because i think one thing that good
comedians do is they call attention to
the form of life that inculcates our
experience and conditions it
unthinkingly
right the forms of life that that that
that um you know the proponents of our
habits the proponents of
the way that we behave the the
structures
we live by that go unseen by us
um through most of our days are
precisely those
i mean good observational comics that's
what they do in effect right they call
our attention down to the fundaments to
the to the to the rudiments that
structure our behavior
and then turn our attention back to
those things it's it's
i mean i don't mean to over attribute
brilliance to the genre but there is a
certain amount of socratic self-inquiry
that good comedians induce and induce
very deliberately well i've heard it
said
um that tragedy is the art that reminds
us of our capacity for transcendence
and comedy is the art that reminds us of
our finitude
uh so that we never think of ourselves
as gods and then remember jonathan
miller saying
if you want to present a tragedy well
try to highlight the comedy in the play
yeah you want to present the comedy well
try and
try and highlight the tragedy within the
show because
and isn't that isn't that the most
dialectical thing
is horrible i mean it's totally tragic
you know where and i guess i guess
tragedy uh
always has this beyond the tragic
so so they there's might be an inverse
there or
well i don't think there is a
dialectical relationship between tragedy
and comedy and that they kind of it's
almost a yin yang
i don't mean that one's yang but you
know the way the yin and yang
interpenetrate and interdefine each
other
um because i i mean this is what um
this is what drew highland argues is the
core of socratic dialectic
because he wrote a book called
transcendence uh
trans what is it transcendence and the
finite or transcendence of finitude
the point is that plato is always trying
to keep us moored both
in our capacity for transcendence and
our mortality as finite beings
because if we give into if we give in to
just the finite
we become enslaved to despair and if we
give in to just the transcendent
we become inflationary and arrogant and
destructive
uh-huh that makes sense yeah
interestingly those two things can
sometimes combine
into the morality tale
what the tragedy of comedy yeah
yeah because because
what you've described is the dialectical
relationship between them and that
dialectical relationship does seem to be
essential to the narrative form
and sometimes those two are collapsed
and then reformulated into a
a third model that becomes a morality
play i'm not saying that every morality
play has
constitutes itself in that dialectic but
some of them do
and when it when when that happens i
think that that synthesis is remarkably
powerful for that reason
well i was thinking of dante when you
said that ex well there we go
yeah i couldn't think of a better
example than that
right so we have the divine tragedy in
the divine comedy in a sense
and they interweave with each other and
you know what we now describe we've now
described the bible
that that that's usually a sign that
we're on to something
[Music]
well i did want to sort of i wanted to
come back to the the
the connection of art and religio i
wanted to yeah
i wanted to and i wanted to distinguish
between
individual expression which really kind
of talked about in
community tasks in terms of art and um
art is a as a something you create with
with people and then art is something
that you do in in
solitude and so
well i mean like i've been making an
argument throughout that art
is a specific although kirkegaard
says and dante says that art and
philosophy can overlap
but i was arguing that art is a specific
way of producing
drawing out and educating right
um religio our our sense of
connectedness
mattering being connected to something
beyond ourselves yep that's that's been
my argument throughout
a really fundamental connection uh
between maybe religion itself
is a collective art could you say that
that's that's often what i think i i i
think i
found myself arguing in various
locations
that
sometimes it's very poor art right i
mean
in churches these days it's like there's
not much you know often it's
but when it's really beautifully done
and powerful
it it it it has the same perhaps
function as
as as a concert or something well that's
because i think you're looking at
uh i think you're looking at an old
religion that is creaking
um but let's say that religion is is uh
is is uh ritual art where
where ritual means there's communitas
involved and distributed cognition
um i think the place to look for this i
was i spoke at the movement summit a
couple weeks ago
and i was just overwhelmed and that is
the correct verb
right uh by the number of people there
who were this was all about
the these are all people who are coming
out of
communities emerging ecologies and
practices and immune
emerging communities about embodiment
and movement
and about self-transformation and the
the
quality and the complexity
uh both within and between all the
speakers and then all
of the various communities that they
were representing and the way they're
networking together
that's what that's the religion that is
now emerging
right now and that is filled with what
we're talking about it's
filled with new kinds of art things that
are you know
like that are moving between
a lot of the established boundaries and
categories and creating new ways
in which people are training and
educating religio that's happening
it's really happening and and
and the emphasis on this being
communitas
is becoming more and more focal in all
of these communities
indeed yeah yeah
one question i wanted to ask you guys is
i wanted since we're talking about art
and reinventing art
if you forgive me to ask a question
because i'm a little bit curious
um i'd just like to know which artists
uh you know
were very formative or moving or
powerful
for each of you or well i just i'm just
curious
so novels uh pessa was very formative
for me herman heston
oh me too and um and melville moby dick
and conrad
those are the three authors uh poetry
overwhelmingly the the greatest
influences are blake and wilka
those are are huge and continual
with me uh and for music
the two most formative influences on me
are beethoven and the beatles
there's so many videos okay great what
about you chris
uh well that's good that's john i'll
just you know what i'll single out one
um
which is um which is a play it's called
our town
wilder which is probably my single
it's actually not just my favorite play
i think it's actually just my single
favorite anything
just piece of art writ large literature
our town it's an american play it's
written in the thirties horton wilder
is the playwright and it's a co
i it is it is actually apropos of
apropos of a conversation from five
minutes ago it
is a cosmic morality play
and i think it's i think it's
it's it's a sacred text to me because i
return to it every few years
and i find that it's it's well spring of
wisdom and insight is deeper than i
could have ever known
five years prior five years before that
five years before that
i keep i keep returning to it like a
well and it um
and it deepens every time for me and it
is i think
it is i think among many other things it
is a dramatic representation
of perhaps the i don't want to be so
reductive as to say it's a play about
the meaning crisis i think that that
would be
that would be unhelpful to say but i
think it's
it is a cosmic morality play very very
simply rendered
about what our relationship is to the
infinite at this moment in time
chris introduced this play to me what
because about five or six years ago
something like that yeah and i agree
yeah
it's a it's a profound work of art it
really is i have never
i've never seen it uh i've never seen it
played
uh i i longed to i'm hoping civilization
hangs together long enough that i get to
watch it
i think it's especially prescient right
now because it's about as it's about the
relationship between
the commune the community tasks it's
about it's about
understanding the it's as much of what
we've been talking about with dialogues
in fact it's about what the relationship
is the
what is what is the affinity between the
interpersonal intimacy of comunitas
and our intimate relation with the
divine and
and it's not when i say it's a morality
pit i don't mean to say that it's
true and didactic and moralizing i don't
mean it that way
it's very unassuming in fact it's the
most unassuming piece of writing i think
i've ever read
it makes it makes it is not
self-aggrandizing
um it's it's it is i think it's perfect
in its simplicity
it's descriptive but in its description
it's um it's i think it's hallowed i
think it's just beautiful
it never loses the human touch with the
finite
while also extending beautifully towards
the transcendent that's right and it and
it is among other things about
even though it never once uses this word
it is about that you were talking before
about andrew about the loss of
symbolic thinking the loss of the
symbolic experience the open
the open-ended experience with the world
and you know
it's interesting because the first two
acts of the play
unbeknownst to the to the to the reader
or unbeknownst to the audience member
take place in this world in which such
things are are
are forgotten and then there's a moment
at the end of the play where one
character
has the opportunity to recollect the
world
with that symbolic porosity with the
shining quality
of of of a world that is
alive and that refers itself to the
infinite she has the opportunity to live
in the world with it shining forth the
infinite to her
and it's an it's just i
i i can't i can't even read the play
without choking it really i can't
so anyway i highly highly highly
recommend it
that's amazing beautiful chris it's very
much
go ahead john's right i'm just going to
say those beautiful chris you really do
have such a beautiful soul
oh my god wow
yeah actually only in the best company
we had one discussion where we were
analyzing you know some
some banal tv show and you had this
insight into the show
i think it was it was this movie the
marriage i thought
wow this guy should be working in
theater like like
you should you should be you should be
making these these productions or
something like that
well that's very kind of working
[Music]
i really think what needs to happen in
the near future is for jonathan and
christopher to have
uh idea logos i think that's what the
discord the discord folks were telling
me that actually
i think i think that is a very astute uh
proposal
on their behalf but i i agree with it i
think that you and jonathan should have
a deep discussion about the symbolic and
the art
and what that its connection to the
sacred and everything you just
you just spoke there yeah you always
your capacity for doing this always
humbles me so
only in the best of company gentlemen
only in the best of company
thank you i i welcome it
[Music]
well gentlemen i i would like to uh talk
longer but i should get going
okay i'm
my last question is is there any loose
ends here is there anything that
any part of uh like our reinvention i'm
not sure if i
fully got the dialogical part of or
i'm not sure if that was fully uh
expressed this time but i'm not sure
what business i'm there yet with that
this is my takeaway
i mean i think there was an argument in
this new way that we're trying to argue
that what we've been playing with or
reorienting from the product to the
process
reorienting from understanding beauty in
the product
to beauty in the process and then that
brought us inevitably to
um very tight connections with virtue
and that's sacred and religious
and i think that's i think that's a very
good place to come to
sure yeah and and i'm still feeling the
chorus i i think that that was
one of the greatest insights i've i've
been i've one of the insights in these
conversations that i've been thinking
about
the most is this idea of the chorus
which
accompanies you know us while we're
having a conversation in other words
we're not you know alone
okay so uh thanks
thanks so much as always thank you
andrew as always
yeah thank you as always uh putting
these together is always really really
wonderful
and thank you chris too thank you very
much thank you john
both of you gents this is always the
greatest of pleasures
yeah for me too enormous pleasure okay
have a good one okay okay take care of
my friends
we'll talk till the next time yep bye
bye